<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Social | Elegant Architecture]]></title>
  <link href="http://erichgess.github.io/blog/categories/social/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erichgess.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-20T08:57:37-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://erichgess.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erich G. Ess]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Haskell Meetup]]></title>
    <link href="http://erichgess.github.io/blog/2014/03/20/first-haskell-meetup/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-20T08:47:44-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erichgess.github.io/blog/2014/03/20/first-haskell-meetup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night was the first meet up for the San Diego Haskell Users Group.  I have to say that it was a lot of fun and probably the most interesting dev meet up I&rsquo;ve been to so far in San Diego.  I have barely done any Haskell, beyond get the compiler setup on my computer and make &ldquo;Hello, World&rdquo;.  As such, I learned a lot.</p>

<ol>
<li>I reallly love how Haskell allows you to build &ldquo;pipelines of data&rdquo;:  when you chain together several functions, put data into the top function and get the output of the bottom.  This is one of my favorite things to get in F# code and Haskell just seems to make it even easier.</li>
<li>Generic Algebraic Data Types:  something which was mentioned to me when I made a comment about doing a presentation on &ldquo;Algebraic Data Types&rdquo;.  I have no clue what the difference between ADT and GADT is but now I have to find out.</li>
<li>Cabal might be the simplest project management/build management tool I&rsquo;ve yet seen.  Though I&rsquo;ve only looked a little at Leiningen, I think, Cabal fills the same role.  However, I found it much easier to read.</li>
<li>Having a meetup be a 15 minute walk from my apartment is the best.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
